是, 大臣  第1季第5集
大白天下
这份报告我仍然不满意 汉弗莱
I am still not happywith this report, Humphrey.
好的大臣 我们很乐意为您重新起草
Then we shall be happyto redraft it for you.
你们已经重新起草三次了     这么说不准确
You have redrafted it three times.That's not absolutely correct.
准确 伯纳 我会数数 这是第三稿
Yes, it is, I can count.This is the third draft report.
对 就是说先起草了一次
Thereforeit has been drafted once
然后重新起草了两次
and subsequentlyredrafted twice.
别钻牛角尖 伯纳
Don't quibble, Bernard.
我们很乐意起草第三次
We shall be happyto redraft a third time.
还有第四次 第五次 肯定还有第六次
And a fourth and fifth.And a sixth, no doubt.
里面说的还不是我想说的 是你想说的
And it still saywhat you want it to say.
我只想说我想说的       您想说什么?
Not what I want it to say.What do you want it to say?
我们想要它说您想说的
We want it to saywhat you want to.
本部门当然不想要您说您不想说的
Not anything you don'twant to.
不要再绕了
Stop wittering
六周前 研究所找我们要
The Think Tank asked us
公务员过剩的证词
forourevidenceon Civil Service overmanning.
我向公务员一字一句布置了三回
I have briefed a group of civilservants in words of one syllable
每次他们交来的报告都不知所云
and they've sent backan unintelligible report,
和我要他们说的刚好相反
saying the exact oppositeof what I asked them to say.
恕我直言 大臣 如果它不知所云
With respect, how do you knowit says the opposite
您怎么知道刚好相反?
if it's totally unintelligible?
我只想说公务员系统
All I am saying isthat the Civil Service
严重超编 必须裁员
is grossly overmannedand must be slimmed down.
正是 报告也是这个意思
Quite so.That is what the report says.
才不是呢       是 就是
No, it doesn't.Yes, it does.
才不...听好 我说的是分阶段
No, it... Look, what I'm talkingabout is a phased reduction
裁掉20万名公务员
in the Civil Serviceof about 200,000 people.
你到底能不能写进报告里?
Are you going to put thatin this report?
大臣 您本周末拿回去好好研究一番
If you were to takethat draft home and study it,
也许会发现它说的正是此意
you might find that it sayswhat you want it to say.
要是没有呢       那我们只能重新起草了
And if it doesn't?Then we can redraft it.
汉弗莱 坐下
Humphrey, sit down.
我坦率地问 你能坦率回答我吗?
Will you give me a straightanswerto a straight question?
好吧 大臣 只要您不要求我诉诸
Oh, well, Minister, as long asyou are not asking me to resort
简单粗拙或者大而化之的概括
to crude generalizationsand vulgar over simplifications,
比如"是"或"不是" 我将尽全力服从
such as a simple yes ornoI shall do my utmost to oblige.
意思是"是"?
Is that "yes"?
是       好
Yes.        Right.
问题来了       我以为刚才那个就是
Here is the straight question.I thought thatwas it.
你给研究所的证词 会不会支持我的观点
When you give your evidence,are you going to support my view
说公务员严重超编?
that the Civil Serviceis overmanned ornot?
是或不是
Yes orno
讲明白
Straight answer
大臣 您一定要我坦率地讲
If you ask mefora straight answer
我只能说 就目前情况
then I shall say that,as far as we can see,
综观全局 纵览古今
looking at it by and large,taking one time with another,
考虑各部门平均水平
in terms of the averageof departments,
分析总结 也许可以认为
then in the final analysisit is probably true to say
综上所述 概括说来
that at the end of the day,in general terms,
您很可能发现
you would probablyfind that
尽管也许不中听
not to put too fine a point on it,
无论如何 恐怕前景微妙
there probably wasn't very muchin it one way or the other.
现阶段只能如此预期
As far as one can see...at this stage.
到底"是"还是"不是"?
Is that "yes"? Or"no"?
是也不是
Yes and no.
如果不要你坦率回答呢?
Suppose you weren't askedfora straight answer?
那我会尽量争取时间 大臣
Then I should play for time.
汉弗莱爵士
Sir Humphrey.
啊 伯纳 请坐       谢谢
Ah, Bernard, do sit down.Thank you.
你能来太好了       我很荣幸
Good of you to pop in.It's my pleasure.
伯纳 你知道部里那份给
Bernard, you knowthe Department's report
中央政策评估小组的报告吗?
on the Central PolicyReview staff?
知道 汉弗莱爵士
Er, yes, Sir Humphrey.
大臣还没还给我们
We haven't had it backfrom the Ministeryet.
是的 没有      为什么没有?
No, Sir.      Why not?
这个...也许您应该问大臣本人
Er... perhapsyou should ask the Minister.
不 我就问你 伯纳       是 汉弗莱爵士
No, I'm asking you, Bernard.Yes, Sir Humphrey.
你好像吞吞吐吐的 伯纳
You don't seem to be replying.
是也不是 汉弗莱爵士
Yes and no, Sir Humphrey.
伯纳 你在搪塞我吗?       绝对没有
Are you trying to be impertinent?Oh no.
我真想搪塞 会成功的
I would succeed if I tried.
请来杯加冰威士忌       好的 先生 就一杯吗?
Scotch on the rocks, please.Yes, sir. One, sir?
对 就一杯
Yes, just one.
伯纳 大臣在认真批公文吗?
Has the Ministerbeen doinghis boxes properly?
当然 他非常尽责       那到底怎么了?
Yes, he's very conscientious.Then what's going on?
请您去问大臣       我问你
You should ask the Minister.I'm asking you.
但我是大臣的私人秘书 要对他负责
But as the Minister's Secretary,I'm responsible to him.
没错 但你也是公务员
But you are also a public servant.
大臣的平均任期不到11个月 伯纳
The average Minister's tenureis less than eleven months,
你可要干到65岁 对吗?
but yourcareerwill lastuntil you're 65, won't it?
对 我希望能       我也希望 伯纳
I hope so. Yes.So do I, Bernard.
不过 你自己拿主意
However, the choice is yours.
呃 汉弗莱爵士
Er, Sir Humphrey...
能否请教一个假设的问题?
Can I ask youa hypothetical question?
这总是个好办法
That's always a good idea.
好 如果有位大臣 一位完全假设的大臣
Well, suppose a Minister,a purely hypothetical Minister,
不满意本部门
were to be unhappywith a department draft
对某委员会的证词草案
of evidence to a committee.
如果这名大臣企图
And suppose that Ministerwere planning to replace it
自己重写 只参谋政治顾问
with his own draftworked outwith his political adviser
和他的政党...       我真不敢相信
and his party...I can't believe it.
不不 这纯粹是假设
Oh, no, no.It's purely hypothetical.
如果这位大臣打算
And suppose that Ministerwere planning to bring in
拖延交稿 让部里没有
his own draft so close to the finaldate that there won't be any...
不会     不会
Wouldn't...Wouldn't
让部里不会有时间重新起草
be any time forthe Departmentto redraft it forhim.
怎样?
Well?
如果这位假设大臣的首席私人秘书
Suppose this hypothetical Minister'sPrincipal Private Secretary
知道了这份
were to be aware of this
假设的文件 当然是作为机密
hypothetical draft,in confidence of course,
他该不该透露给这个假设部门的
should he pass on this informationto the Permanent Secretary
常任秘书?
of this hypothetical department?
当然不该 伯纳
Certainly not, Bernard.
既然这名首席私人秘书得到的
Not if this Principal Private Secretaryhad been given
属于机密信息
the information in confidence.
我也是这么想的 汉弗莱爵士
That's what I thought,Sir Humphrey.
来一杯 伯纳?
Have a drink, Bernard.
还有件事 大臣
One more thing, Minister.
给中央政策评估小组的报告
The evidence to the CentralPolicy Review Staff.
你说研究所?       对 大臣
You mean the Think Tank?Yes, Minister.
怎样?       您是不是重新起草了您草案的草案?
Have you redraftedthe redraft of yourdraft?
你不是要拿回去吧?       正是
You don'twant it yet, do you?Yes.
为什么?       好为您重新起草
Why?So thatwe can redraft it.
没有必要       我认为有 大臣
Thatwon't be necessary.I think itwill.
汉弗莱 起草文件不是公务员的特权 知道吗?
Drafting is not a Civil Servicemonopoly, you know?
不 这是门艰深的技艺
No, it's a highlyspecialised skill
非公务员很难掌握
which few outsidethe Service can master.
胡说 起草最容易了
Nonsense.Drafts is easy.
人人都能玩一把
It's a game anyone can play.
想不被玩进去就难了
Notwithout getting huffed.
能否请您把草案还给我?
So could I havethe draft proposal, please?
没问题 汉弗莱
Certainly, Humphrey.
什么时候 大臣?       过一阵 汉弗莱
When, Minister?          Later, Humphrey.
对 但是具体什么时候?
Yes, but when?
你总说做事不能操之过急
You always saywe musn't rush things.
大臣 我必须请您坦率答复
I must ask youfora straight answer.
哪天?明天?周一?周二?
On what day? Tomorrow?Monday? Tuesday?
适当的时候 汉弗莱
In due course, Humphrey.
等机会来临
At the appropriate juncture.
万事俱备
In the fullness of time.
条件成熟
When the moment is ripe.
所有必要程序都走完
When the necessary procedureshave been completed.
当然不会贸然给你
Nothing precipitate, of course.
大臣 这事很紧急
Minister, this is getting urgent.
紧急 汉弗莱?今天新词不少么
Urgent, Humphrey?What a lot ot newwords
大臣 请恕我冒昧
You'll forgive me if I say this,
但我开始怀疑
but I am beginning to suspect
您对我隐瞒了什么
that you are concealingsomething from me.
我们两个之间当然没有秘密 对吗?
You and I have no secretsfrom each other, have we?
抱歉 大臣 但有时人不得不想到
I'm sorry, but sometimesone is forced to consider
事情可能受到操纵
the possibility that affairsare being conducted in a way
考虑一切情况 前思后想
whichallthingsbeingconsidered,andmakingallpossible allowances
尽管可能比较刺耳
is, not to put too finea point on it,
也许您不完全坦率
perhaps not entirely straightforward.
坦率不坦率你最懂了
You're the experton straightforwardness.
那给政策评估小组的草案怎么说?
So what aboutthe draft evidence?
好吧 既然你问了 汉弗莱 还问的这么坦率
since you ask, Humphrey,and to be perfectly straightforward,
我自己重新起草了一遍
I have redrafted it myself.
我不要你再改
I don'twant you to redraft it.
我非常喜欢它现在的样子
I'm perfectly happywith it as it is.
我能否斗胆问句您写了什么?
May I be bold enoughto ask what you have said?
就是我想说的 分阶段裁减公务员      对 可是...
What I wanted: Phasedreductions in the Civil Service.
汉弗莱 你挫败了我的透明政府
You have frustrated meoveropen government,
挫败了我的节约运动 这次我可志在必得
and the economy drive,this time I'm going to have my way.
政党需要它 公众也需要
The party wants it,the public wants it.
我不得不说 公务员只会采取拖延战术
And all we get from the CivilService is delaying tactics.
公务员的拖延不能叫"战术" 大臣
I wouldn't call Civil Servicedelays "tactics", Minister,
这是把消极当积极
thatwould be to mistakelethargy for strategy.
很好笑 汉弗莱
Very droll.
但你必须了解 改革是当务之急
But there is a real desirefor radical reform in the air.
党派联席特别行政委员会
The Select Committeeon Administrative Affairs,
由我建立 非常之成功
which I founded,it's a great success.
哦 是吗 有什么成就?
Oh, indeed,what has it achieved?
眼下没有 不过我们党派很喜欢
Nothing yet.But the party's very pleased with it.
为什么?
Why?
首先 上周一《每日邮报》10寸的专栏
Ten column inchesin last Monday's Daily Mail.
如今政府以专栏长度论成败啦?
The government measuresits success in column inches?
是...不是...
Yes... no...
是也不是
Yes and no
大臣 您要提交的证词
Minister, the evidencethat you are proposing to submit
不仅不真实 更有甚者 还不明智
is not only untrue, it is also,which is much more serious, unwise.
这件事我们讨论过
Now, we have beenthrough all this before.
公务员编制庞大
The expansionof the Civil Service
是议会立法的结果
is the resultof parliamentary legislation,
与官僚帝国无关
not bureaucratic empire building.
就是说下次质询 你要我告诉议会
So you want me to tellParliament that it's theirfault
是他们害公务员队伍这么庞大?
that the Civil Service is too big?
可这是事实 大臣       我不要事实
But it's the truth.I don'twant the truth.
我要给议会一个交待
I want somethingI can tell Parliament.
汉弗莱 你是我的常任秘书 应该执行我的政策
Humphrey, you are supposedto enact my policies.
可我不明白 你怎么专门跟我作对
Yet, you seem implacablyopposed to them.
我必须知道你站在那边
I must knowwhereyou stand on all this.
大臣 一个人站的立场 取决于他坐的位置
Where one stands, Minister,depends upon where one sits.
我猜你是不支持我了?
Am I to inferthat you will not support me?
我们永远支持您 大臣
We will always support you,
但要给您扛旗 而不是抬棺材
but as your standard bearernot as you pall bearer.
汉弗莱 你在说什么呀?
What are you saying?
我认为再清楚不过了 大臣
I should have thoughtis crystal clear.
不要把报告交给
Do not send this report to a body
打算发表它的人
whose recommendationsare to be published
我就是要拿去发表
That is exactlywhy I'm sending it.
我不想再听你说了
I don'twant to hearany more.
我能否再说一件事?       拜托用人话说
May I say just one more thing?Lf it's in plain English.
很好 大臣
Very well, Minister.
如果您非要做这件蠢事
If you are going to dothis damn silly thing,
拜托别用这种蠢办法
don't do itin this damn silly way.
大臣 内阁会议您要迟到了
Minister,you'll be late forCabinet.
哦 对了 内阁
Oh, yes. Cabinet.
今天上午讨论什么?
What are we talking about?
内阁讨论您的提案 关闭土地局
Yourproposals to close downthe Land Registry.
我的提案?
My proposal...?
您记得吗 缩减地方自治政府
Reducing the autonomousGovernment Departments.
是你的提案       您签字了
Itwas yourproposal.You have initialled it.
哦 是吗?写的什么?       放心 大臣 绝对一致通过
Oh, have I? What's in it?It'll all go through on the nod.
好吧 东西带齐了?       齐了
Got all the stuff?         Yes.
快点 可别迟到
Come on then,mustn't be late.
小汉
Humpy...
你们部给研究所的证词写了吗?
Have you written yourevidenceto the Think Tank yet?
多少算吧       怎么讲?
More or less.What do you mean?
大臣在写       小汉
The Minister's written it.Humpy
对对 很不明智 可他一定要写
Yes, I know. All very unwise.But he insisted.
他一个多星期就没干别的
He's been working at nothing elseformore than a week now.
你不该让大臣卷进这么深
You should never let Ministersget so deeply involved.
今天写草案 再不盯紧 他们要定政策了呢
The next thing you knowthey'll be dictating policy.
是 我明白
Yes, I know.
这次会议长吗?       估计不会
Is this a lengthy Cabinet?I don't think so.
纯粹浪费生命
Ghastly waste of time.
没错 可没有我们牵着小手
Yes, but if we're not hereto hold theirhands,
天晓得他们会干出什么来?
God knowswhat they might not get up to?
失陪了 巨人 是 大臣
Excuse me, Jumbo.Yes, Minister?
你知道我提议内阁关闭土地局吗?      知道
I'm recommending to Cabinetto close down the Land Registry.
为什么?       为什么?
Why?             Why?
为什么关闭还是为什么提上内阁?
Why are we closing itorbringing it to Cabinet?
什么?       什么?
What?           What?
我为什么要提上内阁?
Why am I recommending it?
您当然知道       不知道我才问
Surely you know.No, that's why I'm asking.
你说会一致通过 我才提的
You said itwould gothrough on the nod,
现在首相问起来了
now the PM's startedasking questions.
我自己还没读过
And I haven't read my proposal.
因为地方政府部门扩张了9.75%
There was a 9.75 rise in autonomousGovernment Departments.
对对 谢谢你
Yes, of course. Thank you.
抱歉 巨人
I'm sorry, Jumbo...
你们在限制地方自治政府?
Helping to restrictthe autonomous departments?
正好跟首相的政策走
That should find favourwith the PM policy-wise.
哦?为什么?
Oh? Why?
最近时兴削减公务员
Veryfashionable simplifyingthe Civil Service
特别是研究所出报告之后
especially with this Think Tankrecommendation.
报告还没提交吧       提交了 私下的
But they haven't reported.Yes, they have, unofficially...
不会 证词还没收集全呢
They haven't takenall the evidence yet.
中央政策评估小组高贵的头脑
The Central Policy Review Staffdon't sully their elevated minds
掺不进证据这种沙子
with anything as sordid as evidence.
估计他们正建议首相
You may take it thatthey'll be advising the PM
简化政府行政部门呢
to simplify the administrationof government.
那我有得忙了 对吧
Well, that'll keep me busy.Ah, well.
我估计不会
I shouldn't count on it.
你不指望我－首相的资深政策顾问
You surely don't expect me,the PM's Senior Policy Adviser,
把机密透给一个常任秘书吧
to betray confidences.
当然 透机密怎么能找同事
Not to yourcolleagues, certainly.
反正午饭前你也会听到小道消息
No doubt the grapevinewould inform you by lunchtime.
听到?听到什么?
Inform?Inform us of what?
汉弗莱 你那位大臣千方百计
Your Minister is seeking
裁减公务员队伍
to reduce overmanningin the Civil Service.
这回他大功告成了
Well, he's going to get his way.
财政部 内政部和公务员系统
Treasury, the Home Officeand the Civil Service
都提议
have all proposed
废除你们行政事务部
to abolishyourDepartment of Administrative Affairs
首相对提案微笑了
and the PM is smiling on the plan.
真荒唐       干净利落
That's absurd.Clean. Dramatic.
众望所归 没什么阻力
Very popularpolitically.No real inconvenience.
你们所有的职能都将由其他部门接手
All yourfunctions could besubsumed by otherdepartments.
吉姆・哈克大公无私 牺牲自己
Jim Hackerwill win throughwith a self sacrificing policy.
首相大概会把他踢到上院 供起来
The PM will probablykick him upstairs.
神风敢死队哈克阁下
Lord Hackerof Kamikaze.
丹尼尔 这一点都不好笑
I hardly think that's funny,Daniel or likely.
怎么?他领导过反首相运动吧
Why not? He ran the leadershipcampaign against the PM.
这可是首相精彩的一笔 一条龙服务
This could be the PM's masterstrokein one fell swoop.
先招安 再封爵 最后架空
Approbation, elevationand castration.
你知道首相的座右铭
You know the PM's motto
"败则怀恨在心 胜则反攻倒算"
"In Defeat, malice.In Victory, revenge".
废除我的部门
Abolish my Department.
想都不要想
Out of the question.
绝对做不到
Simply can't be done.
你当然最清楚 汉弗莱
I'm sure you knowbest.
顺便 马贩街有个就业中心
By the way, there's a job centrein the Horse ferry Road.
19路公交 下车即到
The No. 19 Busstops right outside.
我太震惊了       您还震惊
I'm appalled.You're appalled?
我才震惊呢
I'm appalled.
真不敢相信 我...太震惊了
I just can't believe it.I'm... I'm appalled.
伯纳 你怎么想?       我震惊了
What do you make of it?I'm appalled, Minister.
我也是 震惊啊
So am I. Appalled
实在是让人震惊
It's appalling.
震惊...
Appalling.
我简直没法形容
I just don't knowhow to describe it.
震惊了?      震惊了 可这是真的吗?
Appalling.But I mean is it true?
他不是吓唬你吧?
Sure he wasn't having you on?
一个部门怎能说废就废
They can't abolishthis entire department.
听起来很像真的 对吧?
It rings true, doesn't it?
我刚看到了各部门联合提案
I've just see the jointdepartmental proposal.
白厅里最不缺提案
Whitehall's full of proposals.
丹尼尔・休斯是首相的亲信
Daniel Hughesis very close to the PM.
会发生什么?我会去哪呢?
What's going to happen?Where will I go?
有个传闻 大臣
Well, there is a rumour,Minister...
传闻?什么传闻?
Rumour? What rumour?
工业协调总管大臣
Ministerwith responsibilityforlndustrial Harmony.
工业协调?
Industrial harmony?
你知道这是管什么 罢工啊
You knowwhat that means.That means strikes
今后全英国的罢工都是我的错
Every strike in Great Britainwill be myfault.
那太好了
Oh, marvellous.
您想过我会怎样吗?
Have you consideredwhat might happen to me?
没 怎样?       八成会调到农渔部去
No. What?I shall be sent to Ag and Fish.
余生都用来讨论鳕鱼配额
The rest of my career dedicatedto arguing about the cod quota.
至于你 伯纳
And as foryou, Bernard,
你的大臣落了地 你现在的好名声
if your Ministerbites the dustyourreputation as a high flyer
也全打水漂
will be hit for six.
你余生大概都要
You'll spend yourcareer
呆在斯旺西(威尔士南郊)的交通管理中心
in the Vehicle Licensing Centrein Swansea.
都是你的错       我的错
It's yourfault.         Myfault?
是你提议削减地方自治部门
Itwas yourproposal to reducethe autonomous departments.
是您提议分阶段削减公务员
You proposed phased reductionsof the Civil Service.
我们还是别吵了 想想现在怎么办?
Don't let's argue about that.What are we going to do?
我们可以上书
We could put a paperup.
往哪上?
Up what?
太妙了       大臣 您倒说一个?
BrilliantHave you any suggestions?
我不知道 我...       震惊了?
I don't know, I'm...Appalled?
大臣 这次我们真的要齐心协力
I do think thatwe should worktogetheron this.
这话我听过       什么意思?
I've heard that before.What do you mean?
你所谓齐心协力 就是你出主意我出力
You telling me what to do,me doing it.
不是的 大臣       你也没办法?
That isn't true.You've no suggestions?
我提议让伯纳叫你的政治顾问来
Bernard could fetchyour Political Adviser.
弗兰克?你要我请教弗兰克?       是的拜托 大臣
You want me to consult Frank?Yes, Minister.
还有 大臣 恕我直言...
And Minister, with respect...
别跟我说这个 汉弗莱
Don't use that language to me,Humphrey.
说什么?       我知道什么叫"恕我直言"
What language?I knowwhat "with respect" means.
你在暗示我的建议全都不值一提
That anything I suggestis beneath contempt.
啊 大臣
Ah, Minister.
这次我是真想齐心协力
I really do meanthatwe should work together.
我需要您       你说真的?
I need you.Do you mean that?
是 大臣       汉弗莱 你太好了
Yes, Minister.Humphrey, how very nice of you.
大臣 如果首相要搞阴谋
Minister, if the Prime Ministeris behind a scheme,
光凭白厅制止不了
Whitehall on its owncannot block it.
内阁大臣的阴谋很容易制止...重新起草
Cabinet Ministers' schemesare easily blocked... redrafted,
但首相就另当别论
but the Prime Ministeris anothermatter.
我们得从议会和白厅两面出击
We need to fight thisin Westminsterand in Whitehall.
弗兰克・埃瑟尔动员后座议员
And Weisel might be ableto mobilise the backbenchers.
对对 媒体呢 他也许还能发动媒体
Yes. And he might be ableto mobilise the Press.
弗兰克 你听到消息了?       伯纳刚告诉我
You've heard the news?Bernard just told me.
有什么建议?
What do you suggest?
我想不出来...我震惊了
I can't think of anything...I'm appalled.
我们不能跟老母鸡似的自乱阵脚
Mustn't all flap aroundlike a lot of wet hens.
得设法拯救这个部门
We've got to savethis Department.
听好 你找组织秘书动员后座议员
I want you to getto the backbenchers
趁它出世之前消灭掉
to put a stop to this thingbefore it starts.
对不起 大臣 可是没出世的东西消灭不着
I'm sorry, but you can't stopsomething before it starts.
多谢了伯纳 弗兰克...
Thank you. Frank...
没那么容易 吉姆 后座议员非常欢迎这计划
Itwon't be that easy.Itwill be a very popularmove.
发动舆论呢?大臣 您知道:
A publicity campaign?You know:
"行政救国" "公文之乐"
"Administration Saves the Nation""Red Tape is Fun".
整版广告登在...
Full page ads in...
我瞎想的
Itwas just an idea.
"公文之乐"?
"Red Tape is Fun"
"公文连起你我他"呢?
What about "Red Tape holdsthe Nation together"?
没办法挽回了 已经大白天下了
Well, there's no doubt about it,the writing's on the wall.
反正公众应该感激行政部
The public should think kindlytowards Administration,
解决了欧通卡的事       就是
because of the Europass.Quite.
欧通卡?       欧洲统一身份证
Europass?European Identity Card.
伯纳 你没告诉大臣?
You've informed the Minister?
大臣 您没看公文盒?
Didn't you do yourboxes?
没有 我在起草草案的草案呢
No, I was redraftingthe redraft of the draft.
简单说 大臣 欧盟即将颁布
Well, Brussels is about to decree
一种新的欧洲统一身份证
that there is to be a newEuropean Identity Card
供欧洲共同体全体成员使用
to be carried by all citizens of the EEC
外交部已经准备妥协了
The Foreign Officeis ready to go along with it
补偿我们硬栽出去的黄油山
as a quid pro quo fora dealover the buttermountain,
红酒湖 牛奶海
the wine lake,and the milk ocean,
羊肉战 鳕鱼堆
the lamb war,and the cod stink.
很显然 首相要您来提出立法
And the Prime Ministerwants youto introduce the legislation.
我?       对
Me?           Yes.
众所周知您是亲欧洲派嘛
You're pro Europe, you see.
这也能大大简化行政程序
And itwould simplifyouradministration.
实在是好主意       好主意?
So it's a good idea.    Good idea?
好主意?       好主意?
Good idea?       Good idea?
有什么不好吗?       这是政治自杀
Not a good idea?     Political suicide
让英国人都带身份证?
Trying to make British peoplecarry Identification Papers?
他们会说这是极权国家的做法
They'll call it a Police State.
我们打了两次世界大战 就为这个?
Is this whatwe foughttwo world wars for?
大臣 这就跟驾驶证差不多
It's little more than a sortof driving licence.
这是给我落井下石
It's the last nail in my coffin.
您可以改叫它"欧洲快车"
You might get awaywith calling it "Euroclub Express".
伯纳 要么闭嘴要么出去
Bernard,eithershut up orget out
为什么是我们 不该归外交部吗?
Can't the Foreign Officeintroduce it?
其实 首相原本也这样想
Thatwas the Prime Minister'ssuggestion,
但外交部长说归内政部
but forthe Foreign Secretaryitwas a Home Office matter
内政部说其实
and forthe Home Officeitwas essentially
这是行政事务 首相同意了
and administrative matter,and the PM agreed.
都在踢皮球
Pass the parcel.
里面有定时炸弹 能怪他们吗?
Can you blame themwhen you can hear it ticking?
恐怕按计划 这个身份卡议案
The identity card billis planned to be
会是本部门的收山之作
the last actionof this Department.
反欧洲分子该高兴了
Wonderful ammunitionforthe anti Europeans.
外交部不知道这会分裂大欧洲吗?
Don't the Foreign Office realisethe damage to the European idea?
当然知道 所以要支持
That's why they support it.
外交部该亲欧洲吧?
The Foreign Office is pro Europe,isn't it?
是也不是...原谅我的措辞
Yes and no...if you'll forgive the expression.
外交部亲欧洲 实际是为了反欧洲
The Foreign Office is pro Europebecause it is really anti Europe.
公务员团结在这一理念下
The Civil Service was unitedin its desire to make sure
保证共同市场不能形成
that the Common Marketdidn'twork.
所以我们才打进去       你在说什么?
That's why we went into it.What are you talking about?
大臣 英国的外交目标
Minister, Britain has hadthe same foreign policy objective
500年来没有变过
forat least the last 500 years:
创造一个分裂的欧洲
To create a disunited Europe.
因此 我们联荷兰制西班牙
We have foughtwith the Dutchagainst the Spanish,
联德国制法国
with the Germansagainst the French
联法国和意大利制德国 联法国制德国和意大利
and with the French againstthe Germans and the Italians.
分而治之 您看
Divide and rule, you see.
一贯效果很好 为什么要改变?
Why should we change now,when it's worked so well?
这都是老皇历了吧?
That's all ancient history surely?
对 也是现行政策
Yes, and current policy.
我们必须打进去 从内部攻破
We had to break the whole thing up,so we had to get inside.
我们施加过外力 没有成效
We tried from the outside,but itwouldn'twork.
现在可以从里面把它搅成一锅粥了
Now, we can make a completepig's breakfast of the whole thing.
挑德国反法国
Set the Germansagainst the French,
挑法国反意大利 挑意大利反荷兰
the Italians against the Dutch...
外交部高兴坏了 光辉岁月又回来了
The Foreign Office is terriblypleased, it's just like old times.
但我们都忠于大欧洲理念吧
Butwe're all committedto the European ideal.
诚然 大臣
Really, Minister.
不然为什么要增加成员国?
Why are we pressingforan increase in the membership?
一个道理 就像联合国
Forthe same reason.It's just like the United Nations.
群龙无首 人多嘴杂
The more members it has,the more arguments it can stirup,
它就越发鸡毛蒜皮
the more futileand impotent it becomes.
这也太刻薄了吧       是啊
What appalling cynicism.Yes.
我们一般叫做外交 大臣
We call it diplomacy, Minister.
别的国家会怎么看身份证?
Howwill the othercountriesfeel about identity papers?
它们没意见吗?
Won't they resist too?
没有 德国人正合意 法国人不在乎
The Germans will love it,the French will ignore it,
意大利和爱尔兰乱成一团 根本执行不下去
and the Italians and the Irishwill be too chaotic to enforce it.
只有英国人受罪
Only the British will resent it.
这是成心陷害我       反正也要废你的部
It's a plot to get rid of me.They'll abolish your Department.
也许首相要斩草除根
Perhaps the PM wantsto make absolutely certain.
别神经过敏       大家都要对付你 你也会神经过敏的
Don't be so paranoid.Everyone is plotting against me.
我们支持你 大臣       对 大臣
We're on yourside, Minister.Yes, Minister.
马丁会支持我们       对 马丁在哪?
Martin will be on ourside.Yes, where is Martin?
外交部长大概在下院 大臣 您也该去的
I think he's in the House,Minister, where you ought to be.
我们去找他
Let's go and see him.
真让人震惊 吉姆
This is appalling, Jim.
你就像参孙       参孙?
You've done a Samson act.Samson?
对 你一心想减少公务员 就动手了
You've reducedthe Civil Service bureaucracy.
摧垮整座大厦 埋葬了你自己
You've pulled the superstructuredown and buried yourself.
惨胜不如败       没办法吗?
A Pyrrhic victory.No ideas?
若能帮忙我当然尽力       不过我还不明白欧通卡...
I'd help if I could, but...But the Europass...
说不过去
It doesn't make sense.
首相看不到它会危害政府吗?
Why can't the PM seethe damage?
没错 欧通卡是我入内阁以来
Yes, this Europass issueis the biggest disaster
政府最大的危机
since I asked to join the Cabinet.
您当然不是这个意思 大臣
I don't think you quite mean that.
人人都知道欧通卡行不通
Everybody knowsthis Europass thing won't happen.
但是为了拿破仑奖  首相一定得玩到底
The PM's got to play along with itbecause of the Napoleon Prize.
拿破仑奖?
Napoleon Prize?
北约颁的 五年一次
A NATO Awardgiven once everyfive years.
布鲁塞尔开大会 发金奖牌 10万镑奖金
Gold medal,big ceremony in Brussels.
这次首相呼声最高
The PM's the front runnerthis time.
颁给对欧洲统一贡献最大的政治家
It's forthe statesman who hascontributed most to European unity.
拿破仑以降 如果不算希特勒的话
Since Napoleon.That is if you don't count Hitler.
所以呢?
So? What...?
委员会六周后决议
The awards committeesits in six weeks.
首相不能最后阴沟里翻船
The PM isn't going to rockthe boat until it's in the bag.
"阴沟里不可翻船" (交通管理中心^_^)
You don't put boats in bags.
你说什么 伯纳?       没什么 首相
What's that Bernard?Nothing, Minister.
一旦奖到手 首相马上推翻欧通卡
Once the prize is awarded,the PM will dump the Europasses.
马丁 多少人知道拿破仑奖的事?
Howmany people know aboutthe winnerof the Napoleon Prize?
这是最高机密       你是说人人都知道
It's top secret.You mean everyone.
不是 最高最高机密       就是它了
No, top secret top secret.That's it then.
汉弗莱 你没想到吗?       想到什么?
Humphrey, don't you see?See what?
后座议员 消息泄漏       威尔士民族党?
Backbenchers. Leaks.The Welsh Nationalist party?
不 不 不
No. No. No.
对不起 外交大臣 我过会再来
Oh, I'll come back later.
别 别走 正要找你
No. No.Don't go, the very man.
进来 丹尼尔
Come on in, Daniel.
我有一事请教       我尽量帮忙 大臣
I want to ask youradvice.I'll give any help I can.
但要是木已成舟的事
But if it's about shutting stabledoors afterhorses have bolted,
我也为无力挽回
even I am powerless to help.
这事你能出力
You won't be powerlessin this case.
完全是个道德困局
It's really a sort of moral dilemma.
假设一名后座议员
Supposing a backbencherwere to put down
向首相质询欧通卡的事...
a question forthe Prime Minister,asking whetherthe Europass...
哪个议员?欧通卡是最高机密
Which backbencher?Europass is top secret.
跟拿破仑奖得主一样机密吗?
You mean like the winnerof the Napoleon Prize is top secret?
我想大臣是说假设有议员
The Ministermeanta hypothetical backbencher.
正是 伯纳 谢谢你
Quite so, Bernard.Thank you.
一名假设的议员
A hypothetical backbencher.
对首相提了个假设的问题
And a hypothetical question
问英国是不是会接受欧通卡
asking whetherornot Britainwas going to adopt the Europass.
非常不可能       我同意 非常不可能
Highly improbable.Oh, I agree. Highly improbable.
但如果首相说"会"
But suppose the PMwere to answeryes,
会严重打击国内吧?
itwould be very damagingin the country?
对
Yes.
如果首相说"不会"
And if the PMwere to answerno
在欧洲又很尴尬?
itwould be very damagingin Europe?
对首相个人来说
To the PM personally.
拿破仑奖方向
Napoleon prizewise.
好 如果这个假设的首相预先知道了
Now, if a hypothetical Ministerwere to get to hear
这个假设的问题 他该怎么办?
of this hypothetical questionin advance, what should he do?
唯一办法是保证
The only coursewould be to ensure
没人会质询这个 很明显
that the questionwas not tabled.
压制议员质询 责任重大啊
Serious business,suppressing an MP's question.
不过 没有别的办法
There is no othercourse.
想拦住他 唯一办法也许是
The only way to stop himmight be to get him
消除他的另一个疑问
to put down a question askingthe Prime Minister
要首相澄清传说中
to squash the rumoursabout the closure
废除行政事务部的谣言
of the DepartmentforAdministrative Affairs.
哦 我肯定...你怎么会想到...
Oh, but I'm sure...whatevermade you think...
没问题 我们全力支持
anything but the fullest support...
昨天你还说废除行政部已经提上议程
You said that a plan to abolishthe Department had been put up,
首相还朝它微笑
and the PM was smiling on it.
不 是嘲笑 嘲笑 不是微笑
No, smiling at itSmiling at it, not on it.
这个主意荒谬绝伦
The whole idea was ridiculous.
可笑 不值一驳
Laughable.Out of the question.
开玩笑
Ajoke.
开玩笑?
Ajoke?
当然是玩笑 你不会以为...
You didn't imagine...
那由首相办公室出具的
So that a minute from the PrimeMinister's office confirming this,
澄清谣言的备忘录 会在24小时内
and squashing the rumour,will be circulated to all departments
下发到所有部门吧
within 24 hours.
让大家都看到 一起笑嘛
So thatwe can all share it,jokewise I mean
你真觉得有这个必要吗?
Do you really think it's necessary?
有
Yes.
好吧 肯定有办法的
Well, I'm sure somethingcan be arranged.
我先失陪
If you'll excuse me.
将死他了吧
Checkmate, I think.
一击中的
Game, set and match.
丹尼尔・休斯能做到吗?
Can Daniel Hughes fix this?
首相自己有想法的吧?
Don't Prime Ministershave minds of theirown?
当然
Certainly.
但正像尼克松总统的亲信说的
But as President Nixon'shenchmen once said:
"抓住了他们的要害
"When you've got them by the balls,
他们的意志和头脑就为你所制了"
theirhearts and minds will follow".
不是吗?
Isn't that right?
是 大臣
Yes, Minister.